<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE Plattenliste SYSTEM "Musiker.dtd">

<Plattenliste>

<Platte xml:id="1">
    <Albumtitel> 22, A Million </Albumtitel>
    <Kuenstler> Bon Iver </Kuenstler>
    <Entstehungsjahr> 2016 </Entstehungsjahr>
    <Ort> Koeln </Ort>
    <Plattenladen> Early Bird Records </Plattenladen>
    <Review>After a few years spent working on things other than Bon Iver, time spent sorting out heavy personal issues, and a radical rethink of the style that launched Justin Vernon's project to the upper reches of inidie folk popularity, the always searching musician returned in 2016 with an album that redefined Bon Iver in dramatic fashion. 22, A Million is a complicated and intricate record that features chopped-up lyrics, altered vocals, sped-up samples, alternately shimmering and clipped keyboards, treated saxophones, and the occasional gentrly strummed guitar. Through most of the challenging album, Vernon and his collaborators create miniature structures of sound and space, letting his vocals drift and cascade through sparse and fractured constructs like a lost soul wandering through empty futuristic streets. It's a long way from intimate folk songs recorded in a remote Wisconsin cabin. -allmusic.com </Review>
</Platte>

<Platte xml:id="2">
    <Albumtitel> Palmen und Beats </Albumtitel>
    <Kuenstler> Dexter </Kuenstler>
    <Entstehungsjahr> 2015 </Entstehungsjahr>
    <Ort> Hamburg </Ort>
    <Plattenladen> Slam Records </Plattenladen>
    <Review> Palmen und Beats ist Dexters Instrumentalversion von seinem Klassiker 'Palmen & Freunde'.Es klingt ziemlich genau so, wie wenn du mit deinen Kumpels in deinem Dorf oder deiner Kleinstadt oder deiner Großstadt in einem kühlen Kellerraum abhängst, staubige Platten auflegst und neben der Sportzigarette auch das Mic kreist. Mit dem kleinen, aber feinen Unterschied, dass hier Dexters 1a-Qualitäts-Beats die Grundlagen bieten und am Mic neben dem Produzenten selbst Meister ihres Fachs wie Morlockk Dilemma, Döll, Audio88, Yassin, Fatoni, Mädness, Sonne Ra oder Chefket aktiv sind.Und, nix gegen dich oder deine Kumpels, aber die machen das halt alle schon bisschen was länger und dementsprechend auch besser. - rap.de </Review>
</Platte>

<Platte xml:id="3">
    <Albumtitel> I Put A Spell On You </Albumtitel>
    <Kuenstler> Nina Simone </Kuenstler>
    <Entstehungsjahr> 1965 </Entstehungsjahr>
    <Ort> Berlin </Ort>
    <Plattenladen> Soultrade Recordstore </Plattenladen>
    <Review> One of her most pop-oriented albums, but also one of her best and most consisten. Most of the songs feature dramatic, swining large-band orchestration, with the accent on the brass and strings. Simone didn't write any of the material, turning to popular European songsmiths Charles Aznavour, Jacques Brel, and Anthony Newley, as well as her husband, Andy Stroud, and her guitarist, Rudy Stevenson, for bluesier fare. There are really fine tunes and interpretations, on which Simone gives an edge to the potentially fey pop songs, taking a sudden break for a straight jazz instrumental with 'Blues on Purpose'. The title track, a jazzy string ballad version of the Screamin' Jay Hawkins classic, gave the Veatles the inspiration for the phrasing on the bridge of 'Michelle'. - allmusic.com </Review>
</Platte>

<Platte xml:id="4">
    <Albumtitel> Winelight </Albumtitel>
    <Kuenstler> Groove Washington Jr </Kuenstler>
    <Entstehungsjahr> 1980 </Entstehungsjahr>
    <Ort> Koeln </Ort>
    <Plattenladen> Underground Recordstore </Plattenladen>
    <Review> Grover Washington, Jr., has long been one of the leaders in what could be called rhythm& jazz, essentially R&B-influenced jazz. Winelight is one of his finest albums, and not primarily because of the Bill Withers hit "Just the Two of Us." It is the five instrumentals that find Washington (on soprano, alto, and teno) really stretching out. If he had been only interested in sales, Washington's solos could have been half as long and he would have stuck closely to the melodie. Instead he really pushes himself on some of these selections, particularly the title cut. A memorable set of high-quality and danceable soul-jazz. - allmusic.com</Review>
</Platte>

<Platte xml:id="5">
    <Albumtitel> The Arc Of Tension </Albumtitel>
    <Kuenstler> Oliver Koletzki </Kuenstler>
    <Entstehungsjahr> 2017 </Entstehungsjahr>
    <Ort> Berlin </Ort>
    <Plattenladen> Melting Point Recordstore </Plattenladen>
    <Review> On his sixth album, The Arc Of Tension, the Berlin based DJ, label owner, and producer Oiliver Koletzki yet again presents his remarkable vision of contemporary electronic music, while also assuming the role of a storyteller. The Arc Of Tension speaks to its listener as a singular, self-contained work, which communicates by way of its natural flow and arc of suspense. The latter is mirrored not only in the multifarious narrative of the actual album, but can also be understood as evidence for its creator's long musical history. While Koletzki focused on a diverse range of vocal collaborations on his previous long players, he now moves on to a different form of storytelling, rooted in the quiet confidence of a veteran musician, as well as the hectic lifestyle of a globally in demand DJ. The Arc Of Tension is a qsychonautiv journey through the vrious cintinents of Oliver's consciousness. -forcedexposure.com</Review>
</Platte>

<Platte xml:id="6">
    <Albumtitel> Stakes Is High </Albumtitel>
    <Kuenstler> De La Soul </Kuenstler>
    <Entstehungsjahr> 1986 </Entstehungsjahr>
    <Ort> Amsterdam </Ort>
    <Plattenladen> Red Light Records </Plattenladen>
    <Review> Inter-genre violence was bubbling beneath the surface, overshadowing the turn hip-hop was taking a turn away from what was a mid'90's renaissance of the late '80s golden age excellence, quickly evolving into what is now known as a jiggy era. On "The Bizness' a song featuring the quickly maturing Common before his lyricsl touchstone One Day It'll All Makes Sense- Dave spits "Do not connect us with those champagne-sippin'money-fakers." Hip-Hop was at a crossroads, a precipice and De La were concerned. "Supa Emcees" asked "Whatever happened to the MC?" and cautioned "Mcing ain't for you". It's an album that did it's part to solve what De La were articulating as a problem, ushering in what would become the newer version of the Native Tongues, with multi-production from a young Jay Dee, Mos Def's introduction to most listeners, the aforementioned Common cameo, and hooks from Erykah Badu and Zhane, artists leading the burgeoning neo-soul movement of the time. -allmusic.com </Review>
</Platte>

<Platte xml:id="7">
    <Albumtitel> Awaken, My Love! </Albumtitel>
    <Kuenstler> Childish Gambino </Kuenstler>
    <Entstehungsjahr> 2016 </Entstehungsjahr>
    <Ort> Koeln </Ort>
    <Plattenladen> Underground Recordstore </Plattenladen>
    <Review> Ganz so sicher, dass man noch einmal neue Musik von Childish Gambino zu hören bekommt, konnte man in den vergangenen Jahren gar nicht sein. Sei es der Struggle mit dem eigenen Künstlernamen, das Löschen aller sozialen Kanäle, oder die Fokussierung auf seine Tätigkeit als Schauspieler und Autor im Film- und Serienbiz, es schien, als plane Donald Glover, sein Musiker-Alter-Ego an den Nagel zu hängen. Schließlich kam es dann doch noch zur Ankündigung, das dritte Album des Kaliforniens trägt den Titel „Awaken, my Love!“. Bereits die erste Auskopllung, das Intro „Me and your Mama“ ließ vermuten, dass die neue LP eine andere Richtung als der Vorgänger „Because the Internet“ einschlagen würde. Insgesamt 11 Songs umfasst das Album, Features gibt es keine. Als einziger Beteiligter tritt der Produzent Ludwig Göransson auf, der gemeinsam mit Donald Glover für den kompletten Soundteppich verantwortlich zeichnet. Wir haben uns „Awaken, my Love!“ angehört. - backspin.de </Review>
</Platte>

<Platte xml:id="8">
    <Albumtitel> Mama's Gun </Albumtitel>
    <Kuenstler> Erykah Badu </Kuenstler>
    <Entstehungsjahr> 2000</Entstehungsjahr>
    <Ort> Berlin </Ort>
    <Plattenladen> Soultrade Recordstore </Plattenladen>
    <Review> Since the arrival of Erykah Badu onto the neo-soul scene back in 1997 with Baduizm, commercial music stood up and took notice with an onslaught of similar artists reaching comparable peaks of mainstream success. After taking some time off for introsoection and to raise her son, Badu returned with Mama's Gun, which is a turning point for her in many ways. Gone are the cryptic "Baduizms" that glossed all over her first release, replaced with a more honestly raw Badu singing directly from her heart rather than her head. Sonically, Badu wades out into adventurous territories as well. The results are consistently tasteful, which only helps to prove once again that Badu is miles ahead of the rest. -allmusic.com</Review>
</Platte>

<Platte xml:id="9">
    <Albumtitel> Welcome 2 Detroit </Albumtitel>
    <Kuenstler> J Dilla </Kuenstler>
    <Entstehungsjahr> 2001 </Entstehungsjahr>
    <Ort> Muenchen</Ort>
    <Plattenladen> Optimal Records </Plattenladen>
    <Review> Jay Dee made a name for himself as one-third of A Tribe Called Quest's beat-making faction. Thanks to his work on Common's critically acclaimed Like Water for Chocolate and Q-Tips post-Quest endeavor Amplified, Dee has also established himself as a hip-hop super-producer. While Dee's stock continues to rise, his underground projects have been less fruitful. Though Dee flips a few clumsy bars as well, Welcome 2 Detroit really takes off when he sticks solely to an instrumental script, retouching trumpeter Donald Byrd's "Think Twice" and transforming Kraftwerk's indelible "Trans-Europe Express" into the strippers'-anthem-in-waiting "B.B.E." -allmusic.com </Review>
</Platte>

<Platte xml:id="10">
    <Albumtitel> Everything Is Wrong </Albumtitel>
    <Kuenstler> Moby </Kuenstler>
    <Entstehungsjahr> 1995 </Entstehungsjahr>
    <Ort> Berlin </Ort>
    <Plattenladen> Vopo Records </Plattenladen>
    <Review> For some it was the pinnacle of his career, for others one of a continued string of triumphs. Regardless of how one takes it, Everything is Wrong shows Moby at a definite high point, and if some tracks are much more memorable and involved than others, those successes alone justify the attention and hype he received in his earliest days. Even more noteworthy is that for all that the album is a definite product of time and place, namely 1994-1995, it stands up to further listens for all the further changes in dance since. If there's an ace in the hole, it's the inspired recruiting of former Hugo Largo vocalist Mimi Goese, who had spent the early '90s well out of the public eye. Her turns on "into the Blue" and especially the haunting, evocative album-closer "Ehen It's Cold I#D like to Die" bring out in the best in both musicians. -allmusic.com </Review>
</Platte>
</Plattenliste>
